<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions and considerations upon a sheet, printed for Francis Smith containing a confession of the faith of several catapædobaptists, whose names are thereunto subscribed. As also the absurdities of the doctrine of arminianism, free-will, and general redemption; and that it is a popish doctrine; and their objections briefly answered. By J. H.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86881</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3666A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224279</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897413</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897413</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135678</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86881)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135678)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2501:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions and considerations upon a sheet, printed for Francis Smith containing a confession of the faith of several catapædobaptists, whose names are thereunto subscribed. As also the absurdities of the doctrine of arminianism, free-will, and general redemption; and that it is a popish doctrine; and their objections briefly answered. By J. H.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
                  <author>Humphreys, John, b. 1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Marshal, at the Bible in Newgate-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J. H. = John Humfrey.</note>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to John Humphreys.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Christ Church Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Redemption --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religious disputations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Free will and determinism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135678:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135678:1"/>
            <p>ANIMADVERSIONS AND CONSIDERATIONS UPON A Sheet, Printed for <hi>Francis Smith,</hi> CONTAINING A Confeſſion of the Faith of ſeveral <hi>Catapaedobaptiſts,</hi> whoſe Names are thereunto ſubſcribed. As alſo the Abſurdities of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Arminianiſm, Free-will,</hi> and <hi>General Redemption;</hi> and that it is a Popiſh Doctrine; and their Objections briefly anſwered.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tolle, Lege, Judica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Marſhal,</hi> at the Bible in <hi>Newgate-ſtreet.</hi> 1679.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:135678:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135678:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135678:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135678:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:135678:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135678:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>TO all true Proteſtant and Chriſtian Readers, into whoſe hands this little piece may come; I deſire to let the World know that it is not for the ſake of any Intereſt I have in the World, or in any Sect or Party of People, this day in the preſent Age, that engages me to this preſent Affair: No, let the World know, that I knew long ſince, upon whom I have cast the infinite weight of both my Soul and Body, <hi>viz.</hi> upon <hi>Jeſus;</hi> that is, upon him, as fulfilling, and having fulfilled in his mediatory
<pb facs="tcp:135678:5"/>perſon, the whole Law of Works; and for juſtification of Faith and Love, for me, and for all his Elect that were given to him by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before the world was. The Truths once delivered to the Saints, declared in the Scriptures of truth, witneſſed by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Sons of the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Church, ſince the Apostles days, before the Supremacy of the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> to the five or ſix Centuaries, though then oppoſed by the <hi>Arrians, Neſtorians, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellians, Manichees,</hi> and others, and ſince by the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> the Head of <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> and by the <hi>Kenites,</hi> and pretending Reconcilers of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> and <hi>Papiſts:</hi> I mean the Bridge-makers for a paſſable way for <hi>Papiſts</hi> o're to us, or we o're to them; <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Grotians, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menians,</hi> and all that hang that way, ſince thoſe unhappy names,
<pb facs="tcp:135678:5"/>as well as perſons, received their Being in the World, are the alone and only Motive that carries me into this Affair at this juncture of time: And particularly, by provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, hearing this man, for whom this Sheet was printed, by name Mr. <hi>Francis Smith,</hi> a Stationer in <hi>London,</hi> preaching up at the Field Town, in the County of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> this Novel, Papiſtical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Arminianiſm, Free-will,</hi> and <hi>General Redemption,</hi> and <hi>Conditional Election</hi> in time, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of an <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> or <hi>Catapaedobaptiſt,</hi> if you rather pleaſe; and having then oppoſed him, as to his Doctrine, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him and his Adherents ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born and Heretical, and withal ſcattering the Poiſon of their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in this Sheet, under the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Confeſſion of their Faith, to the ſubverſion of the unſetled
<pb facs="tcp:135678:6"/>and ignorant people, I, as a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to the royal truths of my So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lord <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and for the better information of his Elect, have, according to my poor abillity, caſt in this Mite into the <hi>Corban,</hi> as my Teſtimony to him and his truth, in this lowring yet Evening Tide of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> is my Preſident, <hi>Gal. 2.5, 6.</hi> who would not give place for an hour to the Enemies of the Goſpel, neither did he reſpect any mans perſon; though they ſeemed by their exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal deportment and manners to be ſome body in the peoples Eyes. My Judge is <hi>Chriſt</hi> my Soveraign; my Jury, the twelve Apoſtles, at that great and approaching Seſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when he ſhall again deſcend the pregnant clouds to judge the World, <hi>Acts 1. Heb. 9. ult.</hi> and crown his Saints and witneſſes. If any ſhall think my Language too
<pb facs="tcp:135678:6"/>harſh, or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian, let them know 'tis not the Sword of the Fleſh, but that of the Spirit I fight with. The Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> call'd them in his days <hi>dumb Dogs;</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle of the Gentiles, <hi>Hereticks;</hi> and I call but all ſuch as come forth in any of the VVhores <hi>Trinckets</hi> but <hi>barking Dogs,</hi> who are far worſe than thoſe <hi>dumb Dogs</hi> and <hi>Hereticks</hi> were, becauſe they are ſtubborn Promoters of the Papal Doctrines, though not of Popiſh Ceremonies, according to that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient definition of Hereſic; by that ancient witneſs of truth Biſhop <hi>Groſthead,</hi> once of <hi>Lincoln: He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſis eſt ſententia contraria ſacrae ſcripturae palam docta pertinaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter defenſa.</hi> And as it was ſaid by the Proteſtant Divines of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> concerning <hi>Grotius, Quod Hugo Grotius papizat;</hi> ſo ſay I of all theſe who promote the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:135678:7"/>Doctrines as he did: who inſtead of flying out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> as the Holy Ghoſt exhorts, <hi>Rev. 18.4, 5, 6.</hi> they hover under her inchanting skirts; to whoſe charge, if they repent not, all the Blood of the Martyrs will be laid, as well as to the direct <hi>Papiſts,</hi> when the Lords time ſhall be accompliſhed. And till they have anſwer'd <hi>Jewel, White, Willet,</hi> againſt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in the very ſame points, they ſay nothing againſt me or my Animadverſions, though they attempt a Reply. And ſo Reader Farewel. Thine in what I may, as to theſe truths herein defended, while I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joh. Humphrys.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135678:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ANIMADVERSIONS</hi> and <hi>CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIDERATIONS upon an Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, Catabaptiſtical,</hi> Pelagian, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian, <hi>Papiſtical Sheet, lately pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, entituled,</hi> A Confeſſion or Declaration of Faith; <hi>lately pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to King</hi> Charles <hi>the Second: Printed for one</hi> Francis Smith; <hi>which, becauſe the Doctrine therein contain'd is partly</hi> Papiſtical, <hi>and partly mixed with the Ingredients of of</hi> Quakeriſm; <hi>as</hi> Free-will, Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Redemption, <hi>and falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from Chriſt, and ſuch like Traſh, againſt the Doctrine of the Goſpel, primarily taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and ſecondarily witneſſed to by the</hi> Proteſtant <hi>Chriſtian Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of all Ages, and by the</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs <hi>in the paſt times of Popery; I think fit to declare to the World, for the ſake of Gods Elect, choſen in Chriſt, by the good will and pleaſure of God alone, from before the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the World, to Eternal Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135678:8"/>by the Tranſaction of their ſins by the Father on</hi> Jeſus, <hi>and the free imputation of the Righteouſneſs of the Law, fulfilled in him to them, which they do in his time, when he gives them Faith, receive it by Faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LET me tell you, you <hi>Arminian, Pelagian, Papiſtical Baptiſts,</hi> are not built on the Foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. but upon the Foundation of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and Antichriſt; for the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are true in nothing, but in the Doctrine of the Trinity, as ſaid Mr. <hi>Philpot,</hi> Martyr; and dying men, eſpecially Martyrs, ſhould be believ'd. You peep your Heads out to ſhew your Antichriſtian Horns, becauſe you are in hope, that ſome lately ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured at the Sturn, may counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance your Sect, as being inclinable to the ſame Opinions, as being new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whaſted (by Divine Providence) from the Tranſmarine Territories of <hi>Papiſtry,</hi> upon the Chriſtian <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> Shores; who yet, it is yet to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:135678:8"/>be doubted hath too much of the <hi>Pelagian</hi> duſt of S. <hi>Omers</hi> cleaving to his feet, or ſhooes: But this will fail you in the day of the Lord, when the true Jeſus, Son of God, and Son of <hi>Mary,</hi> High-Prieſt, Prophet, and King, in one Perſon, will plead his own Truths, that you, and ſuch as you, have moſt abominably abuſed and belied.</p>
            <p>Your firſt Article profeſſes Faith in one God, and the Father, of whom are all things; which the <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Mahometans</hi> do acknowledge as much as you, or more. See the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choran,</hi> Chap. 17. entitled, <hi>Of the Voyage by Night;</hi> and Chap. 18. called, <hi>the Chapter of the Cave,</hi> 27, 28, 29, 30 lines.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond, that all the miſery, and death, and condemnation of the World, brought in by the fall of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> is but temporal, corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real, and only as to this life, is a Lye againſt Scripture, Reaſon, and the Authority of good and approved Authors. This Opinion was held by <hi>Jacobus Faber,</hi> and many other
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135678:9"/>
               <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but not by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> Gen. 2. <hi>In the day thou eateſt, thou ſhalt die the death;</hi> is a Hebrew phraſe, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, eternal and temporal death, <hi>moriendo morieris, Eph.</hi> 2.23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.6, 7, 8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.6.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14.17.20.23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5, 14. to 21. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.3. to 9, 10. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. the wages of all. ſin is death in that kind, that the gift of God is life: But the gift of God is life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal to all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed; <hi>ergo,</hi> the wages of all ſin is eternal death, by the Rule of <hi>compar. contrar.</hi> My Authorities are <hi>Calvin Inſtit. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1, 2, 3. the Aſſemblies Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm, <hi>Queſt.</hi> 19. and Anſwer to it: Dr. <hi>Willet</hi> againſt <hi>Papiſts</hi> in his eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth general Controverſie read at large, beſides <hi>Luther, Zuinglius, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon;</hi> and more Ancient, <hi>Auguſtine, Hierom, Chryſoſtom, Ambroſe, Tertul. Juſtin Martyr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third Article profeſſes Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Redemption; that the Father gave Chriſt out of his love to the whole world, and a Ranſom for all univerſally: wherein 1. The Fathers
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135678:9"/>gift is diminiſhed; and 2. The Sons Ranſom belied; for the Father gave him to be a Propitiation for the ſins of the world of the Elect, and none elſe; that is, to all the Elect of <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile:</hi> ſo is all taken, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. definitely; and <hi>John</hi> 17.6, 7. and 10. he gave him to the Sheep only, whoſe ſins he laid on him, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53.6.11.1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24, 25. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. and to whom only he gave and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted his Righteouſneſs, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9, 10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15, 16. The Elect <hi>Jews</hi> were his Sheep; and other Sheep I have, that is the Elect of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles;</hi> and the Reprobates he called Dogs, Wolves, Lyons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which he ranſomed not, neither was given to ranſom; ſo he did more for his Elect than you acknowledge, <hi>viz.</hi> tranſacted and bore their ſins on his own body. 2. He did it not for all, but only for them whom the Father gave to him, and him to them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.2.6.8.9.11.29. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.44.39.37. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.3.11.15, 16, 26, 27, 28, 29. Theſe only by his Blood hath he cleanſed in his ſight, not by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135678:10"/>Water-Baptiſm, but by his Blood, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7.9. and Chap. 5. and of this is the Water of Baptiſm a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure; and by his Blood hath ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Juſtice for all their ſins, paſt, to come, and preſent, and redeemed them; and of this is the Supper a Symbol or Sign, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth Article ſings the ſame Song, wreſting the word <hi>All</hi> to a falſe ſenſe; that God is willing that all ſhould come to repentance, and none ſhould periſh; and that the pardon of ſins ſhould be preached to every Creature, that none might ſuffer in Hell: The Word of God is belied, making it ſpeak what it intends not, and the Goſpel ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticated: For firſt, the Goſpel is miniſterlally offered to all, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. but by recommunication of the Spirit only to the Elect; <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11, 12, 13, 18, 19, 20. with 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.11. To the Elect it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to know the Goſpel, but not to the Reprobate, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.40. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.7, 8, 9, 10. And <hi>Piſcator</hi> a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Divine ſaith, <hi>Gratia affertur
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135678:10"/>à deo, animo communicandi eam folis E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectis hand quaque ſingulis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the fifth; I ſay, degrees of Chriſtianity abſtractively adapt not to the Miniſtry; beſide, I deny you to be a Church of Chriſt: <hi>Ergo,</hi> have no power to give your appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation in Ordination: Beſide, the Church alone, though true, cannot by Divine Authority ordain Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, or Commiſſionate them to go forth to Preach.</p>
            <p>The ſixth Article is ambiguous as moſt of your Preachments are, to deceive the ſimple, and obtain Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelites, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17, 18, 19. <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>melli Hybleo venenum latet:</hi> Faith don't juſtifie, as an Act; nor is it the Root of Juſtification, as <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay; it is Chriſt, and his Perſonal Righteouſneſs, that juſtifies the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, being Elected, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4 <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.33. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1, 2, 3. and they by Faith, when God gives it them, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ.</hi> 2. apprehend and receive this Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, wrote in his Perſon for their juſtification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2.3. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12. where you
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135678:11"/>ſay, Believers commit themſelves to his Grace: I boldly aſſirm, you <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians, Grotians,</hi> and <hi>Pelagians</hi> don't mean, by Grace, to the imputation of his Righteouſneſs, wrought in his Individual Perſon for all his Sheep, and given to them for their juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and received by Faith of them. Thus all true <hi>Proteſtants</hi> but you, with <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and all the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> mean, that the Act of Faith, in this your Opinion and new-fangled Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and Chriſt, with repentance and obedience to your holy Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, this is your juſtification, and the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> for which you will be aſhamed in the day of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, when the Thrones of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the World ſhall bow before him, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. and all that own and receive not his imputed Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhall be ſlain, and caſt in the Lake, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. and 22.15.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh Article tells a loud Lye, like his Fellows; for God gives his Spirit to his Elect Sons, before you do believe, or can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, repent, or obey; for all theſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135678:11"/>are done by the Spirit, or ſome Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er elſe; but no Power elſe but the Spirit can work theſe: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Spirit is given firſt, not before their Redemption, Reconciliation, and Juſtification, but before the Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of this Grace; by the Office of the holy Spirit, this Grace is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, received, and applied to the Elect only, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.10, 11, 12. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.15, 16. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10, 11, 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15, 16. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13.18, 19, 20.</p>
            <p>The eighth Article is ſwoln big with the poyſon of Sophiſtication and Contradiction; and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you hide your Errours under a diſguiſe, like a hitter Pill wrapt up in a little Sugar, or Wormwood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeds in Plumbs, to deceive the ſimple, and Children; for you would make us believe you own the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of God, while indeed you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them. 2. Acontradiction, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if they be Elected for foreſeen Faith, works, or repentance, then it is not of meer mercy, and good will, and nothing in the Creature
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135678:12"/>but ſin: So that the ſecond part of your Article contradicts the firſt, and the firſt is ſophiſticated: You ſay, God Elects from the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world ſuch as believe; that is, when they believe he E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects them, that is, he hath decreed to Elect all that believe; but he E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects them as meer ſinners, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he Elects them they believe, and not that he Elects them becauſe they believe.</p>
            <p>The ninth is like his Fellows, full of falſhood, for they were ordained to Condemnation before they were ungodly men, and becauſe of their Reprobation became ungodly men, becauſe they were afore ordained to deſtruction; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> before decreed, or afore written for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; and therefore became ungodly.</p>
            <p>The tenth lies like the father the ſecond Article. For <hi>Adam</hi>'s fall brought in Eternal deaths as well as Temporal, I ſaid afore; and if all are under that Condemation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.16, 17, 18, 19. <hi>Ex.</hi> 16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.21.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135678:12"/>then Infants for Infants are part of all. Beſide, all that are fallen into Condemation, which all are, cannot be ſaved till they are born again of Water and the Spirit, or baptized with Fire and the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.3, 5. 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. <hi>Ez.</hi> 36. Water, in all which places, is not your Baptiſm, but the clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Chriſt's Blood, applied by the Spirit to the Elect in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion and Regeneration; of which Baptiſm is but a meer figure to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> and his believing Seed, as Circumciſion was before the actual payment of the Debts of the Elect, by Chriſt on the Croſs at <hi>Jeruſalem, Heb.</hi> 13.11, 12, 13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.26. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.54.10, 14. ſee 18 Q. of the Aſſemblies Catechiſm, and Anſwer: Four things iſſue to all <hi>Adam</hi>'s poſterity by his fall. Firſt, The guilt of <hi>Adam</hi>'s firſt ſin. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, The privation of Original Righteouſneſs. Thirdly, A depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the whole nature of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Soul, by Hereditary deſcent. And fourthly, All actual Sins flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135678:13"/>from it, <hi>Ro.</hi> 5.12, 19. and 10. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3. <hi>James</hi> 1.14, 15. <hi>Mark</hi> 15.29. <hi>Ro.</hi> 7. See Doctor <hi>Willet</hi>'s 81 <hi>Gen.</hi> Controverſie againſt <hi>Papiſts;</hi> the Elect have their Sins tranſacted on Chriſt, and his impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Righteouſneſs covering them, and the Spirit of Chriſt in his time converting them to it, and the reſt, great and ſmall, are blinded and damned, <hi>Ro.</hi> 11. The whole Law broken by <hi>Adam,</hi> and his Poſterity in him, comprehends both Faith, and perfect, and ſinleſs obedience; which Covenant being broke, he brought both himſelf and poſterity under Condemnation <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18, 19. tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and Eternal; for ſuch is the Wages of Sin, <hi>Ro.</hi> 6.21. and lying under the breach of the whole Law of God, are eternally condemn'd, except they be elected, called, juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and ſanctified freely by his Grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29, 30, 31.</p>
            <p>Chriſt did not come into the World to ſave men if they would, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. for then none would be ſaved; but he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135678:13"/>came poſitively and abſolutely to ſave them that were eternally given to him to ſave, <hi>Jo.</hi> 17. and <hi>Jo.</hi> 10.26. to 29. Chriſt's death and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions were not Temporal and Bodily only, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.46. and Chap. 26.36, 37, 38, 42. <hi>Mark</hi> 14.3, 4. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.42, 44. <hi>Joh.</hi> 18.11. but Spiritual and Infernal paſſions, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.31. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 16.10. <hi>Lament.</hi> 1.12. And if Chriſt's Sufferings were ſuch, then <hi>Adaw</hi>'s fall muſt procure ſuch: But this Helliſh Doctrine denyeth both: By this Doctrine the Covenant of Grace was made ſince the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> and not from Eternity, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture inculcates, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.1, 2, 3. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 89. and <hi>Zach.</hi> 6.13. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5. and then the Covenant of Grace is but a new Covenant of Works, <hi>viz.</hi> Faith and Obedience; as if Faith was not included in the Covenant of Innocency, and fulfilling the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the pardon of Sin in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, upon pain of Eternal Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo that by this Doctrine the new Covenant of Grace is a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more bondaged, ſervile,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135678:14"/>and legal than the Covenant of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency: For the forfeitures of that, ſay they, was but bodily and temporal, and ſo was Chriſt's death that ſatisfied for it: But the forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of this new Covenant of Grace, according to their Doctrine, is Spiritual and Eternal Damnation, and no help or ſatisfaction neither: in the Covenant of Innocency Chriſt made up the breaches, but the breaches of this Covenant of Grace we our ſelves muſt make up by our Free-will, Faith, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and Obedience, or elſe periſh eternally: And from the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagion, Arminian, Papiſtical</hi> new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, wherein Chriſt is only or chiefly an example, only by his Kingly and Prophetical Offices in Heaven, he prays for me, my Faith, Victory, and Repentance; but if I do it not, or cannot, his Prayer is in vain. And as for his Prieſtly Office, as Dr. <hi>Hammand</hi> ſaith, it dyed with him: For it was only to remove the Covenant of Works, which was by a temporal death
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135678:14"/>eaſily removed, its forfeitures being but a temporal death; from ſuch a New Covenant, Lord deliver me, and his Elect, and from the Promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gators of it. Another Juggle they have is, that Election is not in the Covenant of Works, or from Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, but in Chriſt ſince; that is, they that do believe the Doctrine they preach, believe, repent, obey, and be baptized, are Elected; and this God foreſaw, and knew, and willed: And to uphold this <hi>Babel,</hi> and Whores Doctrine of <hi>Babylon,</hi> they turn upſide-down the very Heart and Entrails of the whole Scriptures, to the laſt of the tenth Article: I ſay the <hi>Jews</hi> were under a Covenant of Grace, and by the ſign thereof, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. brought by Divine Command their Children into the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church. We are under the ſame Covenant of Grace, and the matter and manner of the ſign was changed under the New Teſtament, or Adminiſtration of Grace, but not the Subjects; for then it had been neceſſary that Chriſt ſhould
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135678:15"/>have forbidden Infants Baptiſm, or <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> his Meſſenger, for Chriſt knew it was once commanded as the New Covenant ſign; but he never repealed the Subject, nor his Meſſenger that came before him, or the Miniſters that followed after him; <hi>Ergo,</hi> what is not repealed by Divine Inſtitution, abides ſtedfaſt, as a Nail faſtened by the Maſters of the Aſſembly, given by one Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, Chriſt Jeſus: Therefore till the <hi>Catabaptiſts</hi> prove by Scripture, that Chriſt, or his Predeceſſor <hi>John Bapt.</hi> or his Succeſſors, the Apoſtles, forbid the Subjects in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed, till then you do all of you ſhamefully beg the Queſtion; and you ſhall be with your Antichriſtian Spirit famiſhed for me, before you ſhall have a Morſel from me to feed your Hereſie: wherefore leave that unlawful Trade of Begging, and work for your livings; that is, prove out of the New Teſtament, by Gods Word, that Infants are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded not to be Baptized, or that Circumciſion was not a Sign
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135678:15"/>and Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith. Or, that Baptiſm did not come in the room of Circumciſion; do one of theſe or be ſilent before the Lord for ever: For, becauſe you have rent the Seal of his Covenant, God will rend you and your Sect into a thouſand pieces: This will be the end of you, to periſh in your own Dung, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. Except the Elect among you, and true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, they only ſhall be preſerved, and in due time come out of your <hi>Babylon,</hi> as well as <hi>Rome's or Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land's Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Eleventh Article builds up your Idol Baptiſm, and ſets it on your ſandy Foundation; for there is not one word of Teach before Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe; but contrary, after Baptiſm to Teach, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. latter end: For the firſt word rendered to Teach, is, in the <hi>Greek, Matheteuſate,</hi> that is, Diſciple all Nations. But the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may be asked, <hi>How ſhall we Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple them?</hi> the Anſwer is, Baptize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then teach them to obſerve all things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:135678:16"/>did ſo Diſciple their Children; and Children <hi>Acts</hi> 15. are called Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; and doubtleſs the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt, and the Kingdom of Heaven, is given to the Elect of them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.4, 5, 6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14 20. <hi>Mark</hi> 9.42. <hi>Luke</hi> 17.1, 2. and belongs to them; and therefore the Sign of the Covenant belongs to them, which is the Water of Baptiſm, and the very rantizing or ſprinckling in the Figure is ſufficient, becauſe the Sprinckling the Blood in the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is ſufficient, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. The ſame way that <hi>Abraham</hi> was Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled are all aged ones in all times; that being ignorant of God's Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant never knew it, or received the Figure before: and this by teaching them the Covenant of God, as God taught <hi>Abraham,</hi> and then ſet the Sign on them. But the way to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple Infants, as in that day by Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, ſo in this day by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. Their Children were called Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and ſo are ours Diſciples of right, if the Subſtance of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:135678:16"/>of Grace be the ſame, as it is, for there is no new thing <hi>ſub Coelis;</hi> and our Baptiſm now doth Baptize into the whole Body or Church U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſal, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. that is, into the number of the Elect, and not into particular, viſible Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and when they do actually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, then are they Members of the viſible, particular Church, actual Members; and then, as Baptiſm, ſhadowed out their cleanſing by Chriſt's Blood, and the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it to them in the Womb by God. So doth the Supper, when they believe, figure out Chriſt's Redemption and Satisfaction to them by his Blood, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. <hi>ult.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>ult.</hi> And though the Sacraments be diſtant in Adminiſtration and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of time, yet Satisfaction, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and Cleanſing, was actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally done at once for all the Elect by Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 18.34, 35. with 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 5.6, 7, 8. and yet, I ſay, the Elect have their cleanſing ſealed and ſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Externally, (for the Internal Seal is the Spirit, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.)
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135678:17"/>moſtly in their Infancy, becauſe God imputes Chriſts Righteouſneſs to them in their Infancy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.10, 3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.14. And becauſe Baptiſm is not a Communion Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the Supper is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. hence they did not eat the Paſcal Lamb, till they were able to ſtand on their Feet, eat bitter Herbs, and walk, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. for the Paſcal Lamb, under the old Adminiſtration of Grace, was the Sign of Chriſt's Death for the Elect, as the Supper is now, both figuring out the ſame thing; to wit, the pardon of Sins by Chriſts bearing them, as the Lamb taking them away, <hi>John</hi> 1.29. only that figur'd out the actual time of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of the Elect to come, but the Supper that the actual time is paſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.29. and ch. 10.14. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is Baptiſm the way of making viſible Churches, but Profeſſion of the true Faith of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.11.10.12. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26. By Faith, and not by Baptiſm; you make Baptiſm your Chriſt, and ſo ſlight the Lords Blood, by placing life in the Figures.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135678:17"/>But the Apoſtle, when ſome in his time, ſee 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. did too much magnifie it, he thanked God that he he had not Baptized but a few Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and tells them, His Miſſion was to preach the Goſpel: A more weighty Affair than adminiſtring Baptiſm, though both belonged to him. The Apoſtles never preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up Baptiſm, as the <hi>Catabaptiſts</hi> do: And though Circumciſion did make Diſciples of right, yet it did not make them viſible and actual Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, but Faith in God's Covenant, and the eating the Paſcal Lamb was a, or the, viſible Communion, as the Supper is now to profeſſed Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers. You belie the word of God to prove your own Hereſie. For this you muſt anſwer one day; mark it, Generation was not the way of the <hi>Jews,</hi> intromiting Church-Members, or making them. It was the knowledge of God's gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.6. Faith in Chriſt, as now. Chriſts Prieſtly Office took away the Sins of the Elect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the old Adminiſtration or Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135678:18"/>as well as now under the new. The Covenant was and is ſubſtantially and formally the ſame, only differs diathetically, and by way of Adminiſtration, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.31, 32, 33. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. Why do you lye againſt the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? and ſay, That <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſcriptural Sprinckling,</hi> for, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. as the Blood of ſprinckling purges away the Sins of the Elect, ſo will the Water of ſprinckling ſufficiently figure it out. A little Wax will ſeal a great Leaſe when the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants therein are firmly agreed. do you know what you prate of, the Bond-woman and her Son? You your ſelves are Children of the Bond-woman, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4, The Seed of the Adulterer and Whore, <hi>Iſay</hi> 57.34, 10. and 12. You truſt in the life of your hand, in your Faith, Repentance, and Obedience for your formal juſtification, as all <hi>Papiſts</hi> do; and as the carnal <hi>Jews</hi> did ſuppoſe that the Law of works was given for them to fulfill in their own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and what they failed of it was
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135678:18"/>to be ſupplyed by the Sacrifices and Ceremonies. Thus miſtaking the whole Order and End of the Law, which was to carry them to Chriſt the Mediator, who was ordained in his perſon to fulfill all the Law of God, and that Righteouſneſs of his to be imputed to the Elect for their juſtification, and received by Faith, when God gave it them to believe: And ſo the Law at <hi>Sina,</hi> given in Thunder and Tempeſt, was to ſhew them their Sinfulneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19, 20, 21, 22. and God's Wrath boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt Sinners, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. and 2. ch. who all in <hi>Adam</hi> have violated Gods holy Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. and come ſhort of the Glory of God by it; and to break the Rock of their Carnal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and ſecurity, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. and 20. To bring the Elect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by humbly to ſubmit to Chriſt, the Everlaſting Mediator, on whom the Lord laid all the Sins of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, <hi>Iſay</hi> 53.6, 11. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24, 25. <hi>Mica</hi> 7.18, 19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80. <hi>ult.</hi> and imputes his Perſonal Righteouſneſs to them for their ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135678:19"/>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. Now as they corrupted their Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Grace under the Old Teſtament, ſo do you and your Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, <hi>Pelagians, Arminians,</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> under the New Teſtament: For, the Apoſtle in that Text, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. oppoſes the Covenant of Grace to the Covenant of Works, or to the Law, made by the <hi>Jews,</hi> as a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works, as aforeſaid; and not the New Teſtament or Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Grace againſt the Old; for as they did take the Law for a Covenant of Works, ſo do you the Goſpel; calling Faith, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and Obedience, the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of it; which are freely given to them as Fruits of the pardon of Sins, not procurers; and rejecting the imputed Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, as <hi>Papiſts</hi> do, and make the Acts of your Faith to juſtifie you, which is full of Sin, yea full of Errour and Hereſie; and therefore your Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſhall not profit you in the day of Chriſt, becauſe you are not wholly freed by Chriſt, but Sons of the Bond-woman.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:135678:19"/>
            <p>There were never but two Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, for Matter and Form, that of Works, and that of Grace, directly oppoſite one to the other. The Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Works was never by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution eſtabliſhed to men ſince <hi>Adam</hi>'s fall; but immediately taken up by Chriſt, the Elects Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and laid on his Shoulders, <hi>Iſay</hi> 9. Being freely wrought in and by him for them, is a Covenant of Grace to them, but of Works to Chriſt; who obtained all by his Works for them. This Covenant of Grace hath two Adminiſtrations; one un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Old Teſtament, before the Law at <hi>Horeb,</hi> and after the Law to Chriſt's time in the Fleſh: Then began the New Teſtament and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Grace to the Elect; more glorious by far than the other for Adminiſtration; though in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the very Subſtance of the Covenants, the Stipulator and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator Chriſt, who undertook it for them, the Father gave him from E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.1, 2. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9, 10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29, 30, 31. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 89. <hi>Iſay</hi> 53.6.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:135678:20"/>
               <hi>Zac.</hi> 9.11. and 6.14. In that of Works in Paradiſe, there was Faith and perfect Obedience, but no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, Confeſſion, or Sorrow of Sin, or new Obedience was admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in that; but in that of Grace, there is Faith, but different from that Faith in the Covenant of Works, and new Obedience and Repentance, Confeſſion and Sorrow for ſin ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted of none of theſe, but to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally juſtifie, only Faith in Chriſt receives juſtification, and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and New Obedience follows as fruits of Faith, and of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin, which ſundamentally hangs on Chriſt's bearing ſin away, and ſatisfying for it once for all. Neither doth our Faith, or Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, or new Obedience, make us Righteous, but Chriſt's Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, fulfilling the Covenant of Works in his own perſon, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to us, and received by Faith, as given of God for that purpoſe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.5, 6, 7. Neither is our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, or Confeſſion, or New O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, or ſorrow for ſins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:135678:20"/>any part of our Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs before God, (but as to man) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wrought by the Spirit of Chriſt in us; follow the pardon of our ſins, and our being made Righteous; and follow Faith alſo in this adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Grace publickly, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. and are not the Grounds or Cauſes of pardon or Receivers, but the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Fruits and Effects in the Elect believing. Beſides: The Law at <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reb</hi> was to the <hi>Jews</hi> a conditional Covenant for Temporal Bleſſings, and being broke, incurred Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Curſings; which, as ſuch a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, expired when Chriſt came, and the Paedagogy of the <hi>Jews</hi> ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; only the Law, as in the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Power, of it, as a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Law in the hand of Chriſt and the Spirit, to humble the Elect, and make them ſenſible of their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and miſery, by the fall from the Covenant of Works in innocency, as in <hi>Adam,</hi> the only Hole at which all Curſe, Wrath and Miſery, Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Temporal entred, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. That they may fall on Chriſt, and at
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:135678:21"/>his Feet for all Redemption and Help, out of themſelves; thus the Law continues ſtill, and for want of this Spiritual Ax, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4. to cut down and humble you, that you may appear as nothing but Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands for Hell, it is that you and all your proud Generations have perverted Chriſt's Goſpel, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed a new one, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9. the which makes your caſe worſe, you are inſenſible of it, but glory and triumph in your curſed Bondage, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. Your juſtification is full of ſin, and you make Chriſt to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe a ſinful juſtification, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. and ſo the Miniſter of ſin you make him, while you prate that he removed the Covenant of Works, and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed that, and procured a <hi>Lex re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediens,</hi> a milder Law; that is, that by Faith, Repentance, and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, we may be juſtified; and ſo you make ſin to juſtifie; for all our Faith, and Repentance, and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is but filthy Rags, <hi>Iſay</hi> 64.6. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. and full of ſin: And Chriſt faith, That when they have done
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:135678:21"/>all that's their duty, that is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, to repent, and obey, <hi>Luke</hi> 17. then are they unprofitable Servants. <hi>Ergo</hi> you make ſin to juſtifie when you make Faith actually to juſtifie. 2ly you make Chriſt the upholder of ſin, when you, with the <hi>Papiſts</hi> your Brethren, make Chriſts Blood to purchaſe a ſinfull juſtification; that is, that our Faith, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance ſhall juſtifie. Do you ſee the <hi>Pelagian, Arminian, Papiſtical</hi> Crew! upon what Rocks and ſholes you ſplit your ſelves, and all to bring in a new and another Goſpel to damn you, and to exclude Chriſt's everlaſting Righteouſneſs, or the Law of works perfectly fulſilled in his perſon, to be imputed to poor, ſinful, undone, ruined Worms, for their free and real juſtification.</p>
            <p>Now all theſe Imperfections are covered to true Believers with the ſame Righteouſneſs that covers their perſons, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15. And ſo both they and all their Performances and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, though in it ſelf faulty, is accepted and ſanctified, and all the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:135678:22"/>ſinfulneſs of it and them covered, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 32. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5, 6, 7. This is a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit peculiar to the Elect, who tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe and receive the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs, and not to you that cannot cry <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whoſe Ruine, Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion lingers not, except in infinite Mercy he give you humility and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty of Spirit; Faith in that truth of the true Jeſus, and everlaſting Covenant, and Repentance for your Blaſphemies and Errours, as a Fruit of the pardon of your ſins by their tranſaction on him, and the Evidence of your Faith in receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Righteouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you are freed by <hi>Jeſus</hi> from all ſin and miſery in <hi>eſſe</hi> or <hi>poſſe</hi> coming on you in Gods ſight from <hi>Adam's</hi> fall, or by your own actual and daily Tranſgreſſions, and from all the ſin and ſpottedneſs of all your moſt holy Duties, your Faith, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Repentance, and new Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, though wrought puerly in you by Chriſt's Spirit as true Believers, and freed from allſin, paſt, preſent,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:135678:22"/>and to come, by the tranſaction of them on Chriſt by the Father, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.6. and the imputation of his pure Righteouſneſs to your perſons, received by Faith alone, you are not free indeed by the Son, <hi>Jo.</hi> 8.31, 32. but in Bondage under the Law and Curſe thereof, <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. <hi>ult.</hi> with your Children.</p>
            <p>Your twelfth Article is ſwollen big with an abſolute Errour drawn from the practice of the Apoſtles, <hi>laying on of hands,</hi> not miniſterially, as a ſign of the approbation of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, but as an Apoſtolical practice, which did with them ceaſe, as being fruitleſs and uneffectual, beyond their time, and unpractiſed in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Churches, nor at all upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Record of Command — more than <hi>James</hi> anointing with Oyl, which <hi>Papiſts</hi> make a Sacrament; or Chriſt's waſhing his Diſciples Feet: But becauſe it is ſufficiently confuted by Colonel <hi>Danvers,</hi> a Brother of yours in the water, but I hope in the Spirit built on better Principles, I deſiſt to proſecute further; only I
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:135678:23"/>obſerve this by the way, That your Tribe and Fraternity, having ſinned moſt againſt the Covenant of God's Grace in Chriſt, in founding your ſelves upon <hi>Popiſh, Pelagian,</hi> and <hi>Arminian</hi> Principles, he hath hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened your hearts, and left you to more Horrible Errours than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>Your thirteenth Article is double tongued—runs with the Hare and holds with the Hound; for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, Prayers, and uſe of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, are the duty of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers —but not the immediate du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of damnable Hereticks. For firſt repent, and believe the Goſpel, if you can, according to its primitive Inſtitution, then thoſe follow in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>To your fourteenth Article I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that you have neither the true Form or Power; and if you had the Form and not the Power, it's e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for us to depart your Tents, becauſe they are Tents of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. You have not the true Faith, <hi>ergo</hi> not the true Spirit; <hi>ergo</hi> not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:135678:23"/>the true Love, <hi>ergo</hi> not the true Power. And for your Form it is not Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal or truly Scriptural. Antichriſt's Foundation, ever ſince the falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſeduced the <hi>Galatians,</hi> is that you are built on.</p>
            <p>Your fifteenth Article is a Beggar too, and preſuppoſes that which we cannot grant you, That you are the true Church and Miniſters of Chriſt; 'Tis true, the true Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt</hi> are to be free, and Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, not like your ltnierants, who trade it in the World, and prate of what you know not, and have not obſerved the Apoſtles Rule, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. and 15.16. <hi>verſ.</hi> for you do not <hi>Orthotomounta</hi> rightly cut down in twain the Law and the Goſpel; preaching one to the proud, ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceited Hypocrites, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the humbled Sinners; and as for Hoſpitality, when God ſhall give us Goſel-wages, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.12, 13, 14. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.7, 8. I truſt we ſhall by his help do our duty in that. You preach not the true Jeſus, nor
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:135678:24"/>the true Goſpel, as <hi>Paul</hi> did, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.3.17. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.4.</p>
            <p>The ſixteenth Article oppoſes his Fellow afore-going, and gives him the Lye to his face, where Miniſters are to be hoſpitable—But here you take the means of hoſpitality from them, and tell them, they muſt preach freely. You forbid Tythes, that ſticks in your throats— though Chriſts Covenant daſhed in pieces you can ſwallow down like the <hi>Phariſees</hi> Camel, <hi>ex ungue Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem:</hi> But pray, where are Tythes forbid <hi>(jure Humano)</hi> as a Goſpel Maintenance, if not <hi>jure Divina.</hi> I would Goſpel Miniſters had the Tythes by the godly Magiſtrates An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, it would be no ſin againſt Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I ask you a Queſtion, Did <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> ſin, or not ſin, in giving the Tythes to the Clergy; which thing was done by him: 1. Before the <hi>Roman</hi> Antichriſt aroſe. 2. In love to Chriſt, notwithſtanding that Voice that is ſaid to tell him, that he had by ſo doing ruined the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:135678:24"/>Church. If you ſay it was a ſin, then prove againſt what Law he ſinned? for where there is no Law, there is no Tranſgreſſion. Is it not lawful for Goſpel Magiſtrates to provide for Goſpel Miniſters? if they may not, by what Law may they not? if they may, by what Law may they not give them the Tenths? 1. You'l ſay, perhaps, becauſe the Tenths are the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmans own; it may be when Chriſt hath taken the Kingdoms in his own Power, he will give it up to them; but till then 'tis in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Kings to diſpoſe it as they will, and your duty to be ſubject to them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. And it is a cuſtom, <hi>è memoria hominum,</hi> and therefore not ours, but the Princes; and may not he give it to whom he will? 2. You'l ſay, 'twas an Antichriſtian Maintenance, brought in by the Pope: This Reaſon is of moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valency, could you prove it. For firſt, 'tis apparent that Tythes were given to the Paſtors of Churches, before the <hi>Roman</hi> Antichriſt roſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:135678:25"/>up.—So, you make Baptiſm of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants Antichriſtian, as brought in by the Pope, which was practiſed from the Apoſtles days, and never queſtioned till about the fifth <hi>Cent.</hi> and then by the Inſurrection of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabaptiſts.</hi> See <hi>Calv. Inſtit.</hi> 4. <hi>lib.</hi> 15, 16. Chapters. But to cloſe all, pray why do you bring in, and eſtabliſh the capital Errours of Antichriſt and <hi>Papiſts;</hi> as Free Will, General Redemption, falling from Grace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which were eſtabliſhed by <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berus, Phygius, Hemingius, Bellarmine,</hi> and many other <hi>Papiſts:</hi> Yet wipe your mouths, like the Whore in the <hi>Proverbs; Come, let's take our fill of love, I have offered Burnt-of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings and Peace-offerings to day:</hi> So you, <hi>Come, let's build on their Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, for we are baptized with Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers Baptiſm, and have gathered Churches, and ſeparated from the Church of</hi> England. Don't you know that Separation is not a mark of the Spirit ſufficient to carry you out, <hi>Jude Ep.</hi> 19. No, nor giving your goods or bodies to the fire neither,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:135678:25"/>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13, no, nor the multitude of your Party, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.22. and Chap. 23.20.21, 23, 24. For your pretended holineſs, prayers, and zeal, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.5, 7, 8. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.6.— Now ſeeing you build upon the Foundation of Antichriſt, the very Doctrines of the Whore, and cloath your ſelves with his Scarlet Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verings, hating all that are not of your Sect, eſpecially of the Element of Water, and with her Whores Righteouſneſs, <hi>viz.</hi> that of Works, for Faith and Repentance are our Works for Juſtification; and yet rail ſo egregiouſly againſt others for holding ſome of her Ceremonies and Figures,—which at worſt can't be ſo bad as her Doctrine is; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſweep your own doors, and pluck the Beam out of your own eyes, ye Hypocrites, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.42.</p>
            <p>The ſeventeenth Article cuts its own Throat, for none are more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Hereticks than you <hi>Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Arminians,</hi> that have drunk down the Poyſon of Antichriſt in theſe damnable Principles, which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:135678:26"/>never no true <hi>Proteſtant</hi> held, ſince the Reformation, till <hi>Arminius</hi> and <hi>Grotius</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> and the <hi>Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> in <hi>Muſcovia,</hi> till King <hi>James</hi> his days, who gave a breathing time to the Promulgators of it, and permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it liberty, to the rooting it ſelf in the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Soyls. All the Martyrs died profeſſed Enemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, and charged it upon the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who ever owned it as the Foundation of all their Doctrine. See <hi>Foxes</hi> Martyrol.</p>
            <q>— O! monſtrum horrendum ingens —</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> oppoſed it in the fifth <hi>Cent.</hi> wherein <hi>Pelagius</hi> firſt broach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it in the <hi>Weſtern</hi> World; and being baniſhed from <hi>Rome,</hi> brought it into <hi>Britain.</hi> Not a word of it in the firſt four hundred years after Chriſt, though the <hi>Arrians, Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, Eutychians,</hi> and <hi>Manechees</hi> ſwarmed with damnable Hereſies, yet not a word of this new Goſpel; though I believe the Baſis of it was laid by <hi>Cerinthus</hi> and <hi>Cerbion,</hi> in Primitive times, and by the falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles before the Apoſtles death,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:135678:26"/>as the Apoſtle demonſtrates in his Epiſtles to the <hi>Galatians, Romans,</hi> and <hi>Hebrews.</hi> Therefore we muſt leave to do with you after the firſt and ſecond Admonition, and reject you, as the poyſon of the <hi>Church,</hi> and the greateſt Enemies to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Righteouſneſs, and our preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Souls.</p>
            <p>The eighteenth Article proclaims loudly falling away from Grace, and ſo ſpeakes perfectly the Language of <hi>Rome.</hi> See Dr. <hi>Willet</hi> againſt <hi>Papiſts,</hi> in his Fifth Abſurdity of General Redemption and Univerſal Grace, <hi>pag.</hi> 912 of his <hi>Sinopſis.</hi> This Errour was deteſted by the Fathers of the Primitive Times; as firſt <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius</hi> the <hi>Areopagita,</hi> in his Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Epiſtle to <hi>Apollophanus,</hi> who as he ſays of himſelf, was 25 years of Age at <hi>Chriſt's</hi> death. Next <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> 163 years after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in his <hi>Explic. Queſt. a Gentibus Chriſt. poſitaram, Queſt.</hi> 23. and <hi>Queſt.</hi> 98. he declares againſt it, That the Saints cannot fall away, being once in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Then <hi>Ireneus,</hi> about 182
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:135678:27"/>years <hi>poſt Chriſt lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Cont. Hereſ. pag.</hi> 550. to 558. and <hi>pag.</hi> 564. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingto the Edition at <hi>Baſil,</hi> 571. — And <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> a learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man, <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 200— Then <hi>Tertullian,</hi> about the ſame time, in his Book <hi>Adverſus Hereticos. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Editio Beati Rhenati Pariſus,</hi> 1566. <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>par.</hi> 161.162. — <hi>Nemo ſapiens, nemo fidelis, nemo major eſt, niſi Chriſtianus. Nemo autem Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianus, niſi qui ad finem uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raverit.</hi> And <hi>Origen</hi>— And <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian, Anno</hi> 270. <hi>poſt Chriſtum. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobius, Hilarie,</hi> and <hi>Baſil,</hi> 370. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> 400 <hi>Epiphanius</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtom, Anno Chriſti</hi> 230. and <hi>Anguſtine</hi> in <hi>cent.</hi> 5. <hi>Cyril, proſper,</hi> and <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, 600. and <hi>Bede</hi> 700. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelme,</hi> 1093. ſince the Conqueſt; and <hi>Bernard, Anno</hi> 1140. As in a Sermon on <hi>Can.</hi> 7.9. and <hi>Can.</hi> 3.4. <hi>I held him, and would not let him go, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till I had brought him into my Mothers houſe.</hi> He deſcants thus. <hi>Venerunt flumina flaverunt venti &amp; impegerunt in eam &amp; non cccidit, co quod fundata eſſet ſupra petram, petra autem eſt Chriſtus,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:135678:27"/>
               <hi>Anno Chriſti,</hi> 1616. And <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Calvin, Melancthon, Zuinglius, and Zanchy,</hi> and all the Councils, as <hi>Milivitan. Can.</hi> 3.4. <hi>Jo. Huſ.</hi> and all the Proteſtants beyond the Seas, have wrote againſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and defended the impoſſibility of a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers falling finally. And to ſhut up all, take Chriſts own words, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.26, 27, 28, 29. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, take <hi>Auguſt.</hi> once more, <hi>lib. de cor. rep. &amp; grat. Chap.</hi> 7. <hi>Eorum qui E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecti ſunt, ſi quiſpiam perit fallitur De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, ſed nemo eorum perit quia non fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litur Deus,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4.5. are, with other ſuch places, ſpoken of Hypocrites; as <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.5, 6, 7. which were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver elected, or truly converted and called. Where are you now? can you ſubvert Chriſts words, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.26. <hi>Ye believe not, becauſe ye are not my Sheep;</hi> And <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. latter end; <hi>My Sheep hear my voice, and I know them, and they follow me; and they ſhall never periſh, and none ſhall pluck them out of my hand.</hi> And then for that Text, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. you pervert it,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:135678:28"/>as you do other Texts, to your own deſtruction, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. For every Plant or Branch in Chriſt the Vine, by external profeſſion, that brings not forth the fruit of true Faith, for Faith is the fruit of the Spirit, ſhall be taken away from that profeſſion, to ſome damnable Hereſie or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme: And that Scripture is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in you, and hundreds more of you <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> who ſince you have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken your Baptiſm, and the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Grace of God, are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up to damnable Hereſies, to <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minianiſm, Pelagianiſm,</hi> a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, and ſome to <hi>Quakeriſm,</hi> and flat <hi>Atheiſm:</hi> And therefore this day is that Doctrine of Chriſt fulfilled upon you. O! that God would grant you repentance, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25. it is God that gives repentance; and it is to be feared, becauſe you have ſtoln that Prerogative from God, and placed it in your ſelves, that God will harden your hearts, as he did <hi>Pharaoh's, Rom.</hi> 9. and give you up to believe a lye, that you may be damned, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10, 11, 12.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:135678:28"/>and <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.40. blind your eyes, and harden your hearts, leſt you ſhould be converted: For to him is all Power, and Glory, and Freedom, to do what he will in Heaven and Earth, for ever and ever, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. laſt.</p>
            <p>The nineteenth Article makes proviſion for the poor, and belongs to the Church-wardens and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers of the Poor, and to the Kings Juſtices of the Peace at the Quarter Seſſions, and Monthly Meetings: Nevertheleſs, I deſire to give of my Morſel to every one that wants, and a Cup of Water to a Diſciple in the name of a Diſciple.</p>
            <p>This is the Mode of all Sects and Hereſies, this day in the World, to call all their own Brood Saints: ſo do the <hi>Papiſts, Arrians, Arminians, Socinians, Quakers,</hi> and <hi>Baptiſts.</hi> This is that Chriſt propheſied of, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.11. Loe here is Chriſt, loe there is Chriſt; but you are all deceived, for Chriſt is not confined to your ſecret Chambers, to your Societies, or to your Wilderneſs: he is where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:135678:29"/>the Faith of Chriſt is, which you deny, having brought another Goſpel, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. and are therefore accurſed.</p>
            <p>The twentieth Article profeſſes the Reſurrection from the Dead, which the <hi>Quakers</hi> do ſeem to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; that is, that the Bodies of the Saints that died, ſhall riſe again, and together with Chriſt their Head be glorified; and the Bodies of the Unbelievers be raiſed, and their Spirits and Souls be re-conjoyned, and ſuffer together with the Devils to all Eternity. But ſome of you Baptiſtical <hi>Arminians</hi> do hold, that the Soul is mortal, and dies with the Body, till the Reſurrection,— con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the true Churches confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all Ages, and to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21, 22, 23. ver. If <hi>Paul's</hi> Soul had died with his Body till the Reſurrection, it had been no gain to him to die; for then there had been more gain to have lived, though in a wicked World, becauſe here he by Faith enjoyed Chriſt, and his Soul lived with his Body; but
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:135678:29"/>when dead, his Soul alſo ſlept at leaſt, and then he could enjoy no Communion of Chriſt, till the time of the Reſurrection: But to die is gain; <hi>Ergo,</hi> his Soul did live and enjoy Chriſt immediately after his diſſolution, as verſ. 23. Again, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. after Death comes Judgment, yea a particular Judgment of the particular Soul: but if the Soul die with the body, though but for a time, then no particular Judgment, which the Scripture allows: if the Soul dies with the Body till the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, what need then is there that Chriſt ſhould intercede, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.24. and appear there before God for the Saints, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.20. What does he appear for the dead? then he need not intercede till they live, that is, till the Reſurrection: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, Chriſts Argument to the <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces,</hi> your half Brethren, may ſerve to confute you, God is not the God of the dead, but of the living; <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> the Souls of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> and all do live, though their Bodies be dead, and Chriſt, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:135678:30"/>of his Body, is the Fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, becauſe the Bodies of the Saints ſhall alſo (their Souls being reconjoyned) enter with him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. and the Souls of the damned are now in Hell, <hi>Jude Epiſt. verſ.</hi> 7.2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Souls of Saints are now in glory with Chriſt the Lord. And laſtly, the old Whores Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory is better than your mortality, for a live Dog is better than a dead Lyon, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.4.</p>
            <p>The one and twentieth Article acknowledgeth a general Judgment, but tacitly denieth the particular Judgment, becauſe the Authors of the Article deny the Immortality of the Soul, from the time of the death of the Body, to the general Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, as I ſaid before: <hi>It is,</hi> ſaith Paul, <hi>appointed once for every man to die, and after that death, to Judgment;</hi> that is, every particular man; for the Premiſes is particular, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Aſſumption muſt be parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular: the death he ſpeaks of is a particular death; <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:135678:30"/>that follows is a particular Judgment; which, I ſay, theſe good Gentlemen tacitly deny: It is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, that the Soul ſhould not live a moment; for if the Soul be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, <hi>à parte poſt,</hi> that is, from the inſtant of its infuſion into the Body, it may not deſiſt from life a moment, for then it would loſe its Immortality. If we grant you Mortality of the Soul for a time, they may as well beg its Mortality for ever; for to unreaſonable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that have not the true Faith of Chriſt, grant an Inch, and they will crave an Ell.</p>
            <p>But I paſs to the two and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth Article, which is like a Jewel in a Swines Snout: What, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt ſet upon the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and Antichriſt? it loaths my Soul to ſee it. The Reign of Chriſt in the Kingdoms of the World in his Saints, in a reſtorative Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal manner, before the final diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World, is and ever was the Judgment and Faith of Saints;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:135678:31"/>and not only ſo, but at the general Judgment, when Chriſt ſhall again the ſecond time appear, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. in that glorified body of his, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend from the Throne, in that fleſh he did aſcend with, the innumerable Societies of Saints and Angels, the then living Saints being changed, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. <hi>ult. Phil.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> to meet the Lord in the Clouds of Heaven, and together with him, to return to take the Kingdoms of the World into his poſſeſſion, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. and ſo to judge the Earth, and give his beheaded and ſuffering Sons, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. quiet and peaceable enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the new Heavens, and new Earth, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 63. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. till the ſecond and laſt Trumpet, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. whether numerically for a thouſand years, or leſs, or more, may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputable by ſome; but for the ſum and ſubſtance, hath been owned from the very Apoſtles days by the Fathers; as <hi>Papias, Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> and almoſt, if not all, except <hi>Auguſt.</hi> and <hi>Jerom,</hi> who yet ſpake very favourably fo the <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſts,</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:135678:31"/>or fifth Monarchical Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Licet non ſequamur, tamen dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare non poſſumus, quia mult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticorum virorum iſta dixerunt,</hi> Jer. 23. <hi>Ep. de regnand. ſecundo Chriſti.</hi> But to ſet up this glorious Truth and Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt upon a rotten Papiſtical, <hi>Pelagian, Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> Heretical, Antichriſtian Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, you will receive the reward of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> Mat. 7. <hi>Lord, we have propheſied in thy Name, and caſt out Devils:</hi> but, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting fire, prepared for unbelievers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The three and twentieth Article pleads for the holy Scriptures to be the Rule of Faith and Life; it is one thing to take the Letter of the Scripture, with the Doctrine and ſenſe of the Holy Ghoſt included, and another thing to accept for our Rule the humane gloſſes of mens na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural or deluded ſpirits, the latter of which is equal with their Errour that deny the regular Authority of the Scriptures: The Letter of the Scriptures, and the Spirit of Jeſus,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:135678:32"/>are both in Commiſſion from Chriſt our Prophet to teach his people: they that exclude the Spirit, and pretend the Letter, are as unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate as <hi>Arminians, Socinians, Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and other Carnal Hereticks: but they that reject the Letter, and pretend the Spirit, are ſwallowed up of Enthuſiaſtical Deluſions, as <hi>Quakers</hi> and ſuch like: For whom God hath joyned together, we muſt not dare to ſeparate aſunder, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out incurring the Curſe of adding or diminiſhing.</p>
            <p>The twenty fourth Article pleads for Liberty of Conſcience in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual matters: It is not to be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but that the Saints of God ought to have their liberty to worſhip God; and to hinder them, is the greateſt ſin, next to the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt: but the queſtion is, who are the Saints? 2. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther falſe worſhippers may have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from godly Magiſtrates? 1. Saints are either called to the Faith of Chriſt, and ſo to the profeſſion of it; and ſuch are viſible, though
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:135678:32"/>they may differ among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſome circumſtances: 2. Saints that are Elect, but uncal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, may be among them that are falſe worſhippers, till called: the firſt only worſhip God truly; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe none can worſhip God truly, but ſuch as truly believe in the Son of God, according to the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, and that Record he hath given in the Word of his Son; <hi>viz.</hi> that Chriſt was made Sin, and a Curſe; that he laid their ſins on Chriſt, and ſo freed them, and their Curſe; and ſo that Righteouſneſs of the Law fulfilled in his Perſon as God-man, is imputed to them for their whole Righteouſneſs, which they by Faith alone receiving, are viſible Saints, and do worſhip God truly: they that have not this Faith, though Angels in appearance, are but falſe worſhippers, becauſe the Law of Faith in Chriſt, is the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the whole Law directly, the firſt Table towards God, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. containing firſt four Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that is fulfilled compleatly
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:135678:33"/>in a true Believer: and foraſmuch as Love flows from Faith, ſo is the ſecond Table fulfilled in a true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever; but this fulfilling the Law by Faith in a Believer, is not his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification or Righteouſneſs before God, for that is Chriſts fulfilling it in his Perſon, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2, 3, 4. and Gods imputing it to the ſinner, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5, 6, 7. and Faith as an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument receives it, and applies it to its ſelf: So then the Act of Faith in us doth not juſtifie, for then our Works and the Law would juſtifie, but it is ſtill Chriſt alone that juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. To the ſecond queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the Magiſtrate may reſtrain falſe worſhippers: See <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.20. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5. the Inſtruments of the Church for this purpoſe are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. delivering the proud and contemptible to Satan; and the godly Magiſtrate is but a Ruling Elder, whether in a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation or Nation. Let the Tares grow with the Wheat—ſome ſay is meant of ſecret Hypocrites: but I ſuppoſe that blood-ſhed, conſiſcati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:135678:33"/>or any corporal perſecution in this day, is not to be in any wiſe inflicted on deluded Conſciences.</p>
            <p>The twenty fifth and laſt Article, ſeems to contradict his Predeceſſor; for he allows the Magiſtrate to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh evil doers, and incourage the good, but his Predeceſſor flatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies the Magiſtrate to have any thing to do with matters of Divine Worſhip. Now among the Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to Spiritual Worſhip, three parts for one may be ſuppoſed to be erronious: Now, what is more cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el than falſe worſhip? <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Magiſtrate is to puniſh falſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers, or elſe he muſt not puniſh all evil doers, foraſmuch as ſuch are the greateſt evil doers in quality, if not in quantity, or number. But here lies a Falacy occult to moſt mens judgments; falſe worſhip, ſay they, conſiſts in mode, or manner of worſhip, not conſidering that the greateſt evil in worſhip lies in the ſubſtance, not in the mode: For falſe worſhip conſiſts either in the ſubſtance, as in a falſe Faith, and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:135678:34"/>falſe Principle, or elſe in falſe mode, or manner of worſhip: the laſt is bad, but the former worſt of all, becauſe it is the ground of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; the latter, though true, is but a form of godlineſs, if the former be wanting. Hence all <hi>Arrians, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians,</hi> and the greateſt part of <hi>Rattabaptiſts, Arminians, Free-willers, General Redemptioniſts, Conditional Decretiſts,</hi> and <hi>Quakers</hi> err in the former, though ſome of them may not in the latter; therefore, at beſt, have but a form of godlineſs, and from ſuch we are commanded to turn away; for the Power conſiſts in true Faith, and true Principles, and true love to God and Man, both ariſing from the diphthongued Union between the Soul, and the Man Chriſt Jeſus, by the Spirit of the Lord; and then mode, order, and diſciplinal method will be ſoon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, if the Premiſes be truly grounded, or elſe not.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:135678:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The Doctrine of</hi> Quakers, Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Arminians, Grotians, Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees, Aſſidians, Papiſts, <hi>and</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiaries.</head>
               <p>ABſurdities from your Errours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing, That God gave his Son for all Univerſally, upon condition that they believe, repent, and, obey him; and ſo Election, upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſomething in the Creature; either naturally, as reſtored by Chriſt at once, as the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> or elſe wrought in them by the Spirit, upon the aſſent of their free will, as the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> only by Gods fore-knowledge, <hi>ab Eterno;</hi> but not determination, and free act, and without conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing in the Creature, and particular free Perſonal Election from Eternity, meerly of good pleaſure, without any thing in the Creature, but to be wrought in the Elected, as the purchaſe of Chriſts Blood after Election.</p>
               <p n="1">1. You make Chriſt the Miniſter of ſin, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.17. for you make man's act of Faith, Repentance and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:135678:35"/>Obedience, the formal cauſe of their Juſtification, not only without which <hi>(ſine quâ non)</hi> but by which they are juſtified before God, and not by Chriſts Merits only: But man's act of Faith, repentance and obedience, is ſin, and filthy rags, <hi>Iſay</hi> 64.6. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. <hi>Ergo,</hi> that which is ſin you make to juſtifie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently Chriſt muſt be then the Miniſter of ſin, if his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs alone be not ſufficient to juſtifie (being imputed by God, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Faith) for ſomething that is ſinful, and of man's, muſt help to juſtifie, and Chriſts Merits only make it paſſable and acceptable: ſo then Chriſts Merits makes ſin paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and acceptable, for all our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs is but filthy rags, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 64.6. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. dung and droſs, yea loſs, which is worſe than ſin; for man hath no righteouſneſs, except it be wrought in him by the aſſiſtance of the Spirit; therefore it muſt be that righteouſneſs wrought in man that the Prophet means, and the Apoſtles; <hi>for in him we live, move, and have
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:135678:35"/>our being,</hi> Acts 17. Now the <hi>major</hi> is proved by all the Teſtimonies and Writings of <hi>Arminians, Baptiſts,</hi> of that Sect, and <hi>Pelagians</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and is notoriouſly known; The <hi>minor</hi> is made good from <hi>Iſay</hi> 64.6. and <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. <hi>Ergo</hi> the COn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion is true, That they make Chriſt the Miniſter of ſin.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Abſurdity is, That thoſe of this Errour do make the Souls of Men, before Chriſt's coming, mortal, and to dye with the Body; which is contrary to the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23, 24. worſe than the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> their Purgatory, <hi>For a live Dog is better than a dead Lyon;</hi> and agreeable to <hi>Atheists, Stoicks,</hi> and <hi>Heathens:</hi> Beſides, it makes all Chriſt's Sufferings on the Croſs (as they ſay) to remove the firſt Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of perfect works, and to bring in a <hi>Lex remediens,</hi> a milder Law, to be only Temporal Puniſhment: For ſuch as was our Deliverance, ſuch was his Paſſion, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1. <hi>ult.</hi> to <hi>deliver us from the Wrath to come,</hi> did he die. <hi>Ergo</hi> our <hi>firſt death</hi> is
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:135678:36"/>both Eternal and Temporal. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ſuch was Gods promiſe to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> had he ſtood; ſuch was his puniſhment if he fell. But if he had ſtood, he had life Eternal; <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> falling, Eternal death; beſides, <hi>The wages of Sin is Death,</hi> Rom. 5. and Rom. 6. <hi>ult.</hi> and <hi>James</hi> 1.13, 14, 15. But all man's Sin entered with his <hi>firſt fall, Rom.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the firſt fall is the ground of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Death: And that Unbelief on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is the cauſe of Damnation, is a Lye againſt the Scriptures. For 'tis true, Unbelief is the cauſe of all ſins efficiently — And <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> were damned inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally for Adultery and Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <hi>Ep. Jude</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. and not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentally and directly for Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief in the Son of God: Yea O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginally becauſe they were repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated <hi>from Faith, effectual Calling, and Glory,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10, 11, 12. and becauſe he did not <hi>taſte death for them</hi> nor deliver them, becauſe they <hi>were not elected,</hi> ab eterno, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:135678:36"/>1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.9. <hi>John</hi> 22.40. <hi>Heb,</hi> 2.9. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (v. 10. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>That by the Grace of God he might taſte Death for every Son.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third Abſurdity is, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. then by theſe mens Doctrine the Foundation of God is not ſure, if the acceptance of Chriſt and his Merits depend on mans Free-will; for conditional is not certain, for Faith is no condition on mans part, but a Neceſſary Qualification wrought in the Elect to apply his Grace, and purchaſed by his Blood too, and wholly wrought by his Spirit in them, as effectual Calling, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. <hi>Fph.</hi> 2. <hi>Cratia non offertur Deo ſingulis, animo communicandi eam, ſed ſolis Electis. Piſcator</hi> againſt <hi>Papiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fourth Abſurdity is, That God's Grace is not free, which is by his word declared to be moſt free, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. not at all of our works wrought in us, for then it is not free: Now Election is the top of his free Grace from
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:135678:37"/>whence flows all the other Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and effectual Calling and Glory, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29, 30, 31, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for if it be upon any condition in us, then it is not free; but it is moſt free, <hi>Ergo,</hi> upon no condition in or by us at all, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48. None can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve but who are pre-ordained to live, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8, 9, 10. The Elect are created unto good works, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his good pleaſure, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. <hi>Huberus</hi> and <hi>Hemingius,</hi> the great <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and Patrons of this So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry, ſay, <hi>non abſolué ſtatuit, ſed defixit in Chriſto, ut credant in eo, ſalvi fiant;</hi> but predeſtination is <hi>de ſcientia Dei &amp; voluntate ejus,</hi> and Act of his Will, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4, 7. as well as of his preſcience, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. Whom he knew he did predeſtinate; there is his Knowledge, act of Will, and determinate Counſel; and the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>prius denifinivit prepoſitus,</hi> ſignifies an act of his will, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>pono &amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> by his determinate Counſel; and it was 500 years before this Errour was ſeen or heard in the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:135678:37"/>Horrizon of the World, till in the fifth Century <hi>Pelagius</hi> preached it at <hi>Rome;</hi> and all the Fathers then, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> oppoſed it. Now ſaith <hi>Tertullian, id eſt verius, quod eſt prius; &amp; id eſt prius, quod eſt ab initiis, &amp; ab Apoſtolis.</hi> Then in latter times, about ſix hundred years ago, when <hi>Popery</hi> and the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Whore brought forth her great Baſtard <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> ſhe laid him on the Foundation of this <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitane</hi> Errour: And then in <hi>Germany, Arminius</hi> and <hi>Grotius</hi> lick'd up the Duſt of the crooked Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; and King <hi>James</hi> tollerat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in <hi>England,</hi> then it began to ſpread and infect with its poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous Breath, the Univerſities and Doctors of our Iſland, and then ſince our Vineyard hath been rifled and undertrod by the croaking <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits,</hi> they have filled every Pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle and Lake, not only Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains anf Rivers, with their Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Spawn.</p>
               <p>The fifth Abſurdity, that Man hath power and free will of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:135678:38"/>to believe, and to convert, or help to convert himſelf; he would have all (ſay they, to believe) then all have power to do it, or elſe God mocks them: <hi>All</hi> in that Text is not Univerſal, but Definitive, all the Elect of <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile;</hi> as in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. it is uſed, and ſo is <hi>All</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; for the whole World lies in wickedneſs, but we are of God: there all the World is taken for a part; and Chriſt healed all Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> baptized all; yet <hi>Herod,</hi> and many more, were not by him baptized; all put for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53.11. and <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.40. it is apparent, that God doth harden and ſoften whom he will, and it is no derogation to his Juſtice or Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; for <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. he may do with his Clay what he will; and he only of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers Grace univerſally by the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Miniſtry, but by the Spirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally, only to the Elect, and none elſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48.</p>
               <p>The ſixth Abſurdity, Man may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt his Effectual Calling if he will; and the Juſuit <hi>Hemingius</hi> brings in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:135678:38"/>
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.33. but that Bone will not be ſo picked, for Chriſt ſpeaks that in reference to his external Miniſtry and Manhood, as an external Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; only in that place, and ſo in other places too, you may find him acting the part of an external Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, though he was God bleſſed for evermore.</p>
               <p>The ſeventh Abſurdity, is falling away from Election, and Faith, and Unbelief, the only cauſe of Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. This laſt I have elſewhere anſwered to; but to the firſt part of the Abſurdity, there are a Cloud of Witneſſes againſt Saints falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; for Hypocrites falling away we admit readily, according to which acceptation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. and ſuch like places are to be underſtood. <hi>Tertul. Ireneus, Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Jerom;</hi> yea all the Fathers of the firſt five <hi>Centuaries,</hi> yea and all the Orthodox ſince; and <hi>Bernard,</hi> though living in corrupt times, in the twelfth or thirteenth <hi>Cent.</hi> on <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.4.<hi>v. Venerunt flumina, venti ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verunt, &amp; impegerunt in eam, &amp; non
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:135678:39"/>recidit eò quòd fundata ſupra Petram &amp; ea eſt Chriſtus.</hi> And <hi>Tertul Nemo ſapiens, nemo fidelis niſi Chriſtianus, &amp; nemo Chriſtianus, niſi qui ad finem uſque perſeveravit.</hi> And S. <hi>Aug.</hi> on <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.26. <hi>Eorum qui Electi ſunt, ſi quiſpiam perit, fallitur Deus, ſed ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo eorum perit. quia non fallitur De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</hi> And <hi>Bernard</hi> on <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>Seoum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum tempus pro peccatoribus &amp; inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis ſed ſeoundum praedeſtinatinem pro amicis.</hi> And <hi>Auguſt.</hi> Cent. 5. <hi>Electi ſunt ad regnandum cum Chriſto.</hi> And <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> Cent. 4. <hi>Omnibus qui ſunt ex ejus corpore vitam acquiſivit.</hi> And Auguſt <hi>Illi Chriſto intelliguntur dari qui praeordinati ſunt.</hi> And <hi>John</hi> 10.26, 27, 28, 29. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.2.6.9, 10. and <hi>Jon.</hi> 6.29.37.44. <hi>cum multis aliis, quae nunc longum eſt praeſcriben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The eighth Abſurdity, is general and univerſal Redemption, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Scriptures, and to <hi>Joh.</hi> the 6.37.44. and <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.26, 27, 29. and the whole Chapter; and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4.7. and to <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48. he only <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 9, 10. taſted death for every
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:135678:39"/>Son whom, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. the Father gave him from Eternity. If Chriſt died for all, he either died effectually, or ſufficiently; effectually he did not, becauſe all are not ſaved: ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he did not, becauſe his death only extends to them the Father gave him, who are beloved in the Womb, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. before they have done good or evil: If he died for all, and all are not ſaved, then is his Death and Grace in vain; but that is againſt both the Honour of God, and Dignity of Chriſt. Compare <hi>Iſai.</hi> 49. to <hi>Iſai.</hi> 42.</p>
               <p>The ninth Abſurdity, that Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief is the only cauſe of Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I have ſaid ſomething to this before; but this is contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.12. to <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. to <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.16. Then all the <hi>Gentiles</hi> before Chriſt and Faith was preached, were freed from condemnation, and all the <hi>Jews</hi> too, for ought I know, for Faith was not publickly preached to them till Chriſt came, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. <hi>ult. Acts.</hi> 17.30. and 14.16.17. Then Infants of Unbelievers cannot be
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:135678:40"/>damned; contrary to <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9. for they were ſlain that belonged to the Parents that did not mourn for ſin — and if you ſay that was only but a temporal death. I anſwer, God did not, even under that tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral conditional Covenant, deſtroy his own People that were ſaved by Chriſt ſo raſhly, they were certainly the Reprobates.</p>
               <p>The tenth Abſurdity: Why did the Apoſtle cry, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33. Oh the depths of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> his Counſels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if your Doctrine be the truth? there is no myſtery, no depth in that, for its built on Reaſon, and every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that hath but common Reaſon may fathom it eaſily, that God gave Chriſt for all. 1. To put them into a condition of peace, and re-inſtate them in Innocency, as before the Fall, that they have naturally free will in part, or whole, to convert them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to believe that Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed the Covenant of perfect o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and purchaſed a milder Law, that it they obey the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Chriſt in the Goſpel, and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:135678:40"/>repent, and be ſorry for ſins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, which they all have power to do, if they will, and that but ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, in your ſenſe; for in the ſenſe of Truth, <hi>ſincerely</hi> is to do the Will of God without any flaw; as the word, and the uſe of it, truly imports: <hi>Sincerè, id eſt, ſine cerâ,</hi> all Honey without any drege of wax, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; the firſt word is derived of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dòr ſolis,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſecerno,</hi> to do ones works in the light of the Sun. A Metap. taken from the Eagles, that try their young, by holding them up to Sun-beams, which if they can't endure, they caſt them down as none of their own: it is to do all works, obedience, and repentance, <hi>&amp; quid non,</hi> in the light of Chriſts Righteouſneſs, and Juſtification from all ſin, guilt, and wrath by Chriſt, and then 'tis freely done, and not for any reward; for repent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, obey, is to be juſtified, but ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity is to do them, becauſe I am freely juſtified by Chriſts tranſaction of my ſins, and his perfect Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:135678:41"/>imputed to me: This is the mark of Popery, and Phariſaicality, which in the end will batter you all to pieces. The 2d. word is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſignifies. Innocence, and Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity; as it were <hi>non cornibus fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienſe, ex à privative, and</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>not to ſtick with horns,</hi> or to be puſhed at, as only the innocent perfect Keepers of Gods Law, as freed from <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. <hi>ult.</hi> for except all ſin be clearly aboliſhed, without any ſpot, wrath will break out: Now is your <hi>Arminian</hi> Faith, and Repentance, and Obedience ſo ſpotleſs, elſe wrath will break out upon you one day or other; and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>forum,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>aufero:</hi> as if all ſin muſt be quite taken away, or elſe the work is not ſincere: but Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is our work, becauſe done in us, though by the Spirit. And the Apoſtle in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. ſaith, <hi>The natural man cannot receive the things of God;</hi> which it might, if yours were the things of God; for there is no My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery in your <hi>Arminian, Pelagian, Papiſtical,</hi> and <hi>Socinian</hi> Doctrines,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:135678:41"/>but meerly Reaſon: And that word in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. may be well and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly read, the rational man, or reaſon it ſelf, cannot receive the things of God, for they are a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery; <hi>Pſeuchicos Anthropos,</hi> the rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal man; for the Soul is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Reaſon, and before Faith is given, is rational, but not ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; 'tis Faith in the Blood of Chriſt, wrought by the Spirit of Chriſt, that makes it truly ſpiritual. But <hi>Puck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> anſwers for you to that place in <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. alledged, that the Apoſtle admired, becauſe he knew the depths of Gods Counſels; and that it was beneath ſo great an Apoſtle, not to know the depths of God. I leave his fooliſh Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as not worth the anſwering, and refer you and all your Tribe to Doctor <hi>Willet</hi> againſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> in his <hi>Synopſis</hi> of the Controverſies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the true <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> where all your Doctrine is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwered and confuted, by irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragable Argumentsl, which when you have anſwered, we will prepare new ones for you.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:135678:42"/>
               <p>The tenth Abſurdity: if this uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally be true, then all have power to believe if they will, contrary to <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.3. then all have Faith gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them, and then their unbelief reſiſts Gods gift.</p>
               <p>Conſider which is the greateſt Myſtery, the Doctrine of Election and Reprobation of perſons freely from Eternity, or conditional Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, upon fore-ſight of works or Faith, or the Election of Seed, not perſons, as the <hi>Quakers</hi> prate; <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> would be juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by obeying Chriſt without them, <hi>Quakers</hi> by obeying Chriſt within them. What difference is here, but as much as is between an Heretick or Papiſt, without doors in a plain dreſs, and a Papiſt dreſſed up in a Myſtery, or an arrant Whore in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Womens apparel, <hi>ſic etiam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But neither will be juſtified by the obedience of Chriſt for them, that they ſcorn that any man ſhould pay their debts for them, but give them but leave, and let God have pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and they will pay him all their own way, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:135678:42"/>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider which is moſt for the glory of Gods Juſtice, Truth, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Love, and for exalting of Chriſt, and Gods free grace, for that of neceſſity muſt be the truth, and all men lyars.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider which is moſt for the ſecurity of Gods Children, for that is Gods great care, either to leave all men to their free will; an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention much like the <hi>Popes</hi> Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, of later years, congenerated out of the drunken Pates of filthy dreamers, <hi>Jude Ep.</hi> to overthrow the Grace of God, and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Chriſt imputed; for this Doctrine knows, nor owns nothing of that kind of righteouſneſs; or to ſecure them in the hands of Chriſt without and above themſelves, and he and his Spirit to do all for and in them freely.</p>
               <p>They object, that by <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. are meant two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Peoples. I anſwer with <hi>Calvin,</hi> they do ſo; But the Apoſtle doth not bring them in ſo, but as two Perſons, ſignifying the <hi>Eternal
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:135678:43"/>free Perſonal Election and Reprobation of God;</hi> either Gods will or mans will are moſt prevalent: God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires not the death of a ſinner, yet they do die, becauſe they will not believe, and repent, when the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry bids them; therefore to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that mans is more prevalent, is blaſphemy againſt God; but if Gods Will is, then is there eternal free perſonal Election and Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation. I demand, when did God give this grace to all men? when did Chriſt reſtore all men? if as ſoon as they fell in <hi>Adam,</hi> then all are conceived, and born pure; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to <hi>Pſalm</hi> 51. to <hi>David</hi>'s expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, and contrary to <hi>Pſalm</hi> 58.3. for then the wicked could not err from the Womb; and contrary to <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.15. for then is not iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty bound up in the heart of a Child.</p>
               <p>Now there are a parcel of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minine and Womaniſh Objections drivelling at the unclean mouths of Quaking and <hi>Arminian</hi> Jezabels, all which, were they a thouſand more,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:135678:43"/>and the ſtrongeſt that their Jeſuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Tribe can bring, are anticipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with an Anſwer by our great Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.19, 20. in the 19th verſe is the protoplot of all Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, and the Anſwer in the 20th verſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Octject.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>? Who hath reſiſted his Will then, if it ſtand in the Free and Perſonal Election be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and without any thing in man, or of man? Why then doth he find fault? Or, Why doth he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe us, ſeeing we cannot help it? Or, Why doth he expoſtulate the Caſe with men? As <hi>Why will ye dye?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Anſ. v.</hi> 20. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Yea, ſay you me ſo! <hi>O! man! But who art thou that replyeth againſt God?</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Or that judgeſt from the Truth againſt God, as the Word ſignifies. What will theſe buſie Bodies and Tatlers not ſtick to meddle with God? Shall the Clay oppoſe the Potter? Shall the Ax reſiſt the Hewer? <hi>O! monſtrum horrendum ingens cui lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ademptum!</hi> for indeed theſe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:135678:44"/>Sophiſters have but one Eye.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 1. If Chriſt dyed for all what need preaching? <hi>Acts</hi> 13. <hi>ult.</hi> 48. He that ordained the perſons, hath ordained the end for them, and the means to come, as <hi>via reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandi,</hi> to that end. Let this ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for an Anſwer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 2. If there be a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Election, then they ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and the reſt damned. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>Sape etiam ſtultus opportunè lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur,</hi> Fools may tell truth: and ſo in this do you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 3. This renders God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and unequal. And ſo thought the unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> under the Law, ſo do you under the Goſpel, and with the ſame Irony as the Prophet did them I anſwer you. Go to then, make you a clean heart, and purge away all your ſins clean out of God's ſight; get you a ſinleſs Faith and Repentance; and fulfill the whole Law in your perſons perfectly, and then God will perhaps receive you. But, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, I anſwer, <hi>Who art thou that replyeſt againſt God?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:135678:44"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 4. The Scriptures bids all <hi>repent and believe.</hi> Anſwer, It ſpeaks eſpecially to all the Elect of <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile:</hi> Or miniſterially to all univerſally, but ſpiritually and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually, to the Sheep the Elect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 5. God don't deſire a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner's death, but that he repent. Anſwer, He dont deſire the death of Elect Sinners, nor never did; for he hath loved them with an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting love, <hi>a parte ante &amp; poſt, Jer.</hi> 31.3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 6. Then is God a reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of perſons. Anſwer, So he is: 1. by way of decree; for he reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Abel</hi> and rejected <hi>Cain,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had elected the one, and rejected the other; and ſo the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and hated the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Eſau;</hi> before they did good or evil. Secondly, Officially he reſpects mens perſons; for Miniſters ſhall ſhine as the Stars; and I have ſaid, ye are Gods, to Magiſtrates, and not to all; and the Man is the Image and Glory of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:135678:45"/>to the place and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of an Husband: So is not the Wife as a Wife, and a Woman: See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. therefore they that contend, and deſpiſe, and rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their Husbands, are <hi>meritricious Gentlewomen,</hi> and <hi>Amazon</hi>'s, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Monſters, generated out of corruption and the worſer part of <hi>Evah,</hi> but the works done by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed and juſtifyed Children—he reſpects not their perſons for their works, but for Chriſts Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs imputed he reſpects both them and their works, and will reward them. Neither doth he reſpect the Beauty, Riches, or Wiſdom of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, ſo as to reſpect the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for thoſe things, though good in themſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 7. <hi>He gave himſelf a ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom for all.</hi> Anſwer, for all his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect definitively; which ſhall be te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify'd in their proper times, <hi>Kainois idiois,</hi> that is, when he by his Spirit calls, and doth convert them.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:135678:45"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 8. It is not our works, but Chriſt that works in us Free-will, Faith, Repentance, and new Obedience. Anſwer, Though he does, it is but filthy Rags, <hi>Iſay</hi> 64.6. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. but Droſs, Dung, and loſs, as to our juſtification. Nothing can juſtifie in any Covenant, but a perfect Righteouſneſs performed in a perfect and righteous perſon, that never ſinned, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.2, 3. <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 9. This Doctrine of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Reprobation will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearten people from uſing the means. Anſwer, It will not Gods Elect, but rather hearten them. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, All are commanded mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterially to uſe the means, and have Abilities to do it; yea the blind may hear, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.10, 11, 12, 13. but ſpiritually the Spirit blows where it liſteth, <hi>John</hi> 3. the Spirit is but given to the Sons alone, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. <hi>John</hi> 12.40.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 10. Diſobedience to the Law brought and incurred but tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral puniſhments, but to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:135678:46"/>Eternal puniſhments, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Diſobedience to every, or to one Tittle of the Law, incurs now, and ever did, Eternal Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for <hi>the wages of Sin is Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal death,</hi> and Sin is but a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of the Law; <hi>Ergo,</hi> the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of the Law deſerves Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Death. But the <hi>Jews</hi> as they were under the Law given at <hi>Sinai,</hi> had a Temporal Conditional Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to reſtrain their exhorbitant Spirits, and allure them by Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Bleſſings, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5, 9. There were three ends of the giving the Law at <hi>Sinai.</hi> 1. To ſhew the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of the fall and breach of that Law in Paradiſe; and that at the laſt Day God ſhall in Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Flame, judge the Bodies and Souls of all that fell and are not reconciled by Chriſt, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with his Righteouſneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6, 7, 8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. or for whom he hath not fulfilled it in his moſt ſinleſs and excellent perſon; and ſo it is a demonſtrative Covenant of works, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. ſhewing Sin,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:135678:46"/>and breaking in pieces the ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited carnal hearts of Gods Elect; that they may receive the Grace of God in Chriſt by Faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.24. <hi>Iſay</hi> 42.18, 19, 20. And this was then Externally and Internally, and Spiritually and internally now, in them that are called, <hi>the uſe of the Law,</hi> to bring them (in the hand of Chriſt) to nothing but deſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in and becauſe of ſin and ſelf-impotency within and without, that ſo they may, in emptineſs and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, receive by Faith a full and able rich Chriſt. Which when it hath done by Faith, the Law vaniſhes out of the Conſcience like a baffled Giant, and retires into the Fleſh to curb that to its duty; and is then a Commandment and Law of Love upon the new Covenant heart of a Believer, to freely move him, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the External Rule and Matter of the means, to glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Chriſt in the World, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>the love of Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains us.</hi> Secondly, a ſecond end of the Law at <hi>Sinai,</hi> was to be a
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:135678:47"/>rule to the Elect Believers then, to walk with God, whoſe Heart and Will the Law repreſents. And ſo it was put in the Ark, <hi>A Type of Chriſt,</hi> in whom now the Law is for a Believers Rule. Thirdly, It was given as a Temporal, Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Covenant, to frighten the ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born <hi>Jews</hi> from Rebellion, and to engage them to Righteouſneſs, a thing God did and does delight in: And ſo the breaches were, as in this reſpect, puniſhed, but with a Temporal Death and Puniſhment; and the Performers with Temporal Life and Bleſſings; and as ſuch a Covenant, its <hi>Epoca</hi> began at <hi>Sinai,</hi> and did end when Chriſt came in the Fleſh. The ignorance of this diſtinction is the root of all Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and Hereſies: And ſo it was to the <hi>Jews</hi> under that Teſtament of Grace, as it is now to us under the new and laſt Teſtament of Grace, ſealed and confirmed, not with the Blood of Creatures and Beaſts, but with the Blood of Chriſt, the Son of God, to the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:135678:47"/>everlaſting Comfort of the Elect Believers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 11. This Doctrine, <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Redemption,</hi> ſets all on work to uſe the means and to endeavour. Anſwer, Have ye never read or heard of <hi>Penelope,</hi> that famous Wife, that when her Husband was gone to the <hi>Trojan</hi>-war, and thought to have been ſlain, by his long tarrying, and ſhe having many Woers perplexing her, not delighting her as they do the Ladies of theſe times, was ſpinning; for Ladies, in thoſe more ancient times, were good Houſe-wifes, though now they are many of them Sluts, and ſhe put back the ſharp impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of her Rivals with this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, <hi>That when ſhe had ſpun off her Web ſhe would anſwer them.</hi> Now to prove her ſelf Loyal to her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and deceptious to her Rivals, ſhe unſpun in the Night what ſhe had ſpun in the day. Hence we call all labour in vain, <hi>The ſpinning of</hi> Penelope<hi>'s Web:</hi> And ſuch is the Works and Endeavours of all
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:135678:48"/>unconverted and unbelieving per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever, though not to ſo good an end as hers was; and this is as good an Anſwer as your Objection. Add to it the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Chriſt, <hi>Mark</hi> 7.7. <hi>In vain do they worſhip me,</hi> and of <hi>Jer.</hi> 12.1, 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 12. What if this Doctrine be <hi>Popery,</hi> yet if it be true it is not to be rejected. Anſwer, <hi>Philpot,</hi> the Martyr, ſaid to <hi>Bonner,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> That the <hi>Papiſts</hi> held not one Truth, but the Doctrine of the Trinity, and yet they held this of Univerſal Grace; and the Words of a Dying Man are true, <hi>ut aiunt,</hi> much more of a Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Martyr, and Chriſtian Man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 13. 'Tis Life and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation that ſaves us and makes us like God, and not Opinion. Anſwer, The living Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt are not Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions but Fundamentals, preached by the immediate in ſpiration of the Spirit, confirmed by the ancient Teſtimony of the Prophets, and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:135678:48"/>ſealed with the Signet of real Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles; and atteſted to by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers of the firſt 500 years, and by all the true Churches to this day; and the Scriptures are the rule and ground of Faith, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20. But ſuch is the Doctrine of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, <hi>ab eterno,</hi> and Reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, free and perſonal; a good Life and Converſation built upon Chriſt is the fruit of Chriſts Spirit work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing love in the called Elect: But ſuch a viſible Converſation, built on the Law and mans own Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, or mans Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, though wrought in time, is no other than the ſuperſtructures of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pariſees</hi> of old, and of Miſtical <hi>Papiſts.</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtians,</hi> the Baſtards of the great Whore, in this day, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.1, 2, 3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.26. 'Tis Chriſt's works, Faith, and Converſation, in him that gives life to his—and not that wrought in them, though by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; that does but teſtifie that they have life in Chriſt to the World.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:135678:49"/>
               <p n="14">14 <hi>Ob.</hi> God then made man to damn him. Anſwer with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle; <hi>But who art thou man that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieſt againſt God? Shall the thing formed ſay to him that formed it, why haſt thou made me ſo?</hi> And beſide, the Scripture ſaith, <hi>He that made them, will not ſave them,</hi> Iſai. 27.11.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Ob.</hi> The eaſieſt way is the wrong, but eternal free Perſonal E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection is the eaſieſt. Anſwer, you know not what you ſay, no man is ſaved, no man believes, no man tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repents, but it coſt Chriſt his deareſt Heart-blood, and muſt coſt us the farewel of deareſt delights, and ſin, and the loſs of our own hearts, ſelf, and intereſts, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.28, 29, 30. 2. That that is the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionalleſt way, is the eaſieſt, becauſe all men have naturally reaſon; but your General Redemption, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Election, and Free Will, is the moſt rationalleſt, and agreeable to reaſon; therefore the eaſieſt, and the way of God above reaſon, and is only fathomed by Faith; as <hi>Heb.</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:135678:49"/>11. Chap. appears: <hi>And that gate is ſtraight and narrow,</hi> Mat. 7. <hi>and few enter into it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Ob.</hi> That whatever we do or ſin, we ſhall be ſaved by the way of Election. Anſwer, that is your carping Calumny againſt the Truth; Gods people cannot ſin that ſin that God cannot or will not forgive, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. <hi>ult.</hi> There is a ſin unto death, and a ſin not unto death: the Elect are beloved when they do no good, or evil; they are belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved when they do evil, their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, not their ſins, I mean, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11. and 13. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9, 10. and they are beloved when they do good, and they ſhall do good, becauſe they are beloved, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. two laſt verſes. Again, the Truths of Chriſt believed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and not Errours, is the only ground of ſobriety, righteouſneſs, and godlineſs, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.12. and 13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. And again, pray, <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicite vobis,</hi> look upon your Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocks feet, how much unlike the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:135678:50"/>Devils they are; though, like the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> your Feathers be fine; your envy, your malice, your pride, your errours, your inſtability, your factions and ſchiſmes, and Popiſh Principles, back-biting, whiſpering, tale-bearing, vain diſcourſe, tatling, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. buſi-bodying in other folks matters, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.15. theſe, and ſuch like, are the Ingredients that your holineſs and righteouſneſs is compoſed of, crying out with the Phariſees, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66. <hi>Stand far off me, I am more holier than thou art.</hi> And this is the manners of you <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> moſt of you, in this latter day, and <hi>Quakers,</hi> and others too, the more is the pity. <hi>Ob.</hi> But we love one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Anſwer, O! Do you ſo, ſo do the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> ſo do the arranteſt He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks in the World; and 'tis but ſelf-love, and with diſſimulation nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for to prop up Self, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Self, and ſecure your Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that is dearer to you than Chriſt's Blood, or love: <hi>Prate not thus,</hi> See you what Chriſt ſaith,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:135678:50"/>
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.46, 47. <hi>Luke</hi> 6.30, 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, 36, 37. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.10, 11. and Chap. 4.20. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.40, 41. Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure your life by theſe Scriptures, and deal truly with your hearts.</p>
               <p>Becauſe you have Free Will, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer me theſe Queſtions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Had the Angels Free Will to ſtand or fall? if they had, why did they fall? or did the Elect Angels ſtand by their Free Will, the other having no ſin to tempt them to fall, more than the Elect had? and why are they called Elect that ſtand, and the other not that did fall?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Had <hi>Judas</hi> free will to believe and repent, as much as <hi>Peter?</hi> if he had, why did he not do as <hi>Peter</hi> did? or did Chriſt pray for <hi>Judas,</hi> as he did for <hi>Peter?</hi> Mark that.</p>
               <p n="3">3. When Satan entred <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> had they power to reſiſt and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon him, or not? if they had, why was it ſo great a burden to them, that the one was mad, the other hanged himſelf?</p>
               <p n="4">4. If no ſin be damnable, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:135678:51"/>againſt the Goſpel, how came the Angels to be damned? and how came <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> to be caſt into Eternal Fire, if the ſin againſt the firſt Covenant be only the cauſe of a temporal death and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as is by you aſſerted? <hi>Ocel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los vobis Jehovah aperito, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Per Johannem H.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:135678:51"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
